Welcome back in this next new session in which we talk about two models OSI model and TCP
IP model. So, yeah. So, this will be a little bit long video. So, if you want to take
a, if you want to go to washroom, you can just sit for seven minutes. Open your mind
and just look into that, that what I am going to say, just memorize it, just visualize
that, how things are going to work and don't take any tension. If you go through
my video in months, I am sure, sure, sure, sure that if any interviewer asks you any question
related to OSI model or TCP/IP model, you can give that answer instantly, okay. You can
how again you can re-watch this video as well. But yeah, it will be good if you note it
down in your notebook, important things at first, at first time.
Let's start my video network layers, a definition of OSI and TCP IP model, so yeah, okay.
First start with OSI model, because OSI model is the one that will help you to understand
how things in networking work and understanding the OSI model are found in a second. Open
system interconnection, OSI stand for open system interconnection, okay. Model describes
seven layers that computer system use to communicate over a network. It was the first
standard model for network communication, right. Doctor by all major computer and telecommunication
companies in the least 1980s and officially standard by ISO in 1984. While modern internet
communication primarily relies on the simple TCP/IP model, the OSI seven layer model remains
invaluable. It helped visualize and communicate how network operate, aiding in the isolation
and troubleshooting of network problem. Open, in OSI, signified its known property
nature, prompting interoperability, the seven layer architecture collaboratively transmit
data across cloud, okay. Next, this is how OSI model look like. Application layer, presentation
layer, session layer, transport layer, network layer, data layer, physical layer. Now, here
is the sender. This sends information, it goes from application to physical, then it
leads to receiver side, it receives from below, in physical layer, then it will go to application
layer. This is how work. First three is software layer, okay. Application layer, less
like we have any application, we have browser. We have any information, we have any software.
So, this is which we are seeing, which is we are seeing is called frontend, from which
we can interact. There is a website in which there is a button we can interact by clicking
on that. We have a menu section, we have a box, we have catalog section, we have dashboard,
we have a lot of things in our software. So, we have application layer, which is visible
to us. A presentation layer is the one, that is the part of software layer, this is how
it pleads present to us. Session is how it communicating in a network, transport layer,
it is a heart of OSI model and why it is called, we will discuss in this video, hardware
layer, network layer, data layer and physical layer. Same goes for data layer, now move
it with the application graph. Application layer sits at the very top of the OSM model,
implemented directly by network applications. It is interface for and uses software like
web browser and email tool is provided protocol that enables software, send receive and
present meaningful data to user. So, it is just like a frontend of a website, which we
can see data from back end and visualizing, visualize it. Now common protocol include
STTP is there, STP is there, STP is there, STP is there, STP is there and DNS is there.
Now, post office protocol, file transfer protocol, hypertext transfer protocol, simple
middle transfer protocol and DNS, you have to tell me, what is DNS? It is so common that
is always accessed in interview. Now, this layer also act as a windows for application
service to access their network and display received information. Example include web browser
Skype and instant machine client, it is sometimes referred as the text drop layer, because
you visible in the end side. Application layer is the topmost layer of the STP model,
here it acts as a behalf of sender and work within a network actually on behalf of that.
Application layer is the most, topmost layer in the representing the group of application
data around user to interact with the network, yes. This is what you can see and use
every day. So now you know application layer, you completely, you can explain it very well
that. Sir, if you interact with a server, whatever I am viewing in my laptop right now,
my desktop right now is on application layer. The thing I am visualizing, the, the
highway I can interact with my software, this is our application, this is called application
layer. This will get exclusive for sharing it with the data that need to be transferred
and requesting connection to network services, okay. And we, you have to tell the protocol
is this, some protocol, just whichever. Now, you have to tell me the full format DNS,
okay, just comment down. Okay, move ahead. Now, move to layer 6 and 5, this is present
layer is presentation layer, this layer presentation layer, prepare data for application
layer, okay. So it's just like a cook, presentation layer is like a cook who prepare data
for the application layer defining how device should include encrypting compressed data
for correct reception, okay. So what it, perform, it's encode, encrypt and compressed
data. Remember, three things you do, it takes data from the application layer and format
it to the transmission over sensor layer. So it takes data from application layer, as
we see in this diagram, we have to move back, it takes data from the application layer,
now goes to presentation layer, presentation, take data from the application layer and
depend on that, it encode, compress, encrypt data and transfer it to session layer.
Often called as translation layer, so presentation layer is also known as translation
layer, these noted down, it extracted and manipulate data into required format for network
transmission, so it will change data format as well depend on the required matter, now session
layer, session layer create manage and terminates communication channel, so there is a lot
of sessions which are communicating we wrote system, we will have to, now it will be
decided which should be go on and which should be cut down right now, it is responsible
for opening and closing this session when communication ends, okay. So if you make a
recast, you recast get completed, so this session layer is the one that will decide that
yeah, right now I can communicate, I can end this communication, this layer also established
checkpoint during data transfer, long device to transume from the last checkpoint if interpreted
in so connection establishment, so maintenance authentication and security, now
it is FDM, file transfer access and management, mail service, direct service, these are
some services, let us go more on a presentation as session layer, key functions present
release, as we go through it, it will encrypt, encode, compress, encrypt, transfer data
into cipher from plain text, how secure transmission and back to plain text upon reception
side, using a key compression to visit the number of bits, transmitted optimizing
network efficiency, if you if you're sending a large number of bits, then there is
it will be a higher chances to, there is a collision in an network that you lower some
data, but in a small number of bits with a, then there will be higher chances of availability
in a network, trustless economic data former such as what is called, it is called a
ski, remember to EBC, DIC format and vice versa, ensuring capabilities between different
system, so somewhere, the social layer, but will do as you know, it will the one that
maintain the communication, it will does one that will decide, you have to keep communicating
or not, at that point to data stream, along for identification and efficient risk, synchronization
to prevent data loss, download controller, manage communication between two system, support
half-tift-lucks or full-depth, half-deflexments, one way communicating, like we have a phone
in a, in 90s that, in which at a time only single person can talk, either you can talk
to me or like, there is a walkie-talkie, I hope you know, there is a walkie-talkie that
is used in a government that, at a time, there is a one person can talk, then another
person, in as well as it is used in a military, that then other person, this phone, then
I have to say it is half-duplex, however the, our cell phone is the one that is full-duplex,
my friend is talking to me, and talking to me, and at the same time, I can say and stop
him, by saying that, let me first hear, first hear me, so there is a, this is how, let
me, go to this left, a transport left, so as you see, as you see previously, so it is also
known as the heart of first-hand model, why we will discuss transport, take data from the
threshold left, and break it into segments, now it will break, that your data into a
segment, one that transmitting it, it is a disposal for assembling the segment on the receiving
it, ok.
So, now, in a centre side, it will break the data in a former receiver side, it will join,
it will re-assemble that data, turning it back into usable data first, yeah, and this
only a perform pressure function, flow control, ok, it will adjust that depend on the speed,
depend on the speed of your wired or wireless network, it will, one, who manage the speed,
ok, adjust stationary rate to manage the receiving device, can access speed and preventing
overview, error control, check if data was received incorrectly, and to question retransmission,
if necessary, yes, so every time they make a frames, there is a, what I am going to say
is like, if you want a deep, if you like this course, ok, this comment down that you want
a deep course on this, I can tell you each and every fragment, like every fragment what
it contains, ok, in more linear, linear way, that each packet contain how many bits
of data, and how it is going to transfer from there to there, from source to receiver
set, so if you want and if you like this course first give a thumbs up bit, I do not know
what you have to be, just give a like, or a serid, your brothers from another mother,
comment down that you want a deep course on this, believe me, I am going to put a very
detailed course, if you go through that course, no one can stop you from anything, like
you are the pro, you are the pro, in a network, ok, if you go through that course, but
for that, I want your love, your support, so if I get a lot of comments in this course
that definitely, definitely, I am going to make it, ok, let us back here, flow control
is like the serid told, it have to maintain that according to the speed, according to the
bandwidth, we have to maintain the flow, the error control is the one that it will check
after making a fragment, it will mark it as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, now, if receiver set, I did
not receive a packet of 4 number, then it will send a packet for once again, ok, so this
is how a flow control is maintained, it provides service to the application, I would
say services from network layer data within the transport layer is referred to as segment,
its family role is to end to end delivery of the complete message, including acknowledgement
of successful transmission, entry transmission if error occurs, transfer layer function,
segmentation and resumpling, as we call as we say segmentation and resumpling, fragment
then resumble them, service point addressing, transport layer header, groups or service
point address, to ensure the message, you would have to correct process or application
of the resumpling, as I said, they marked as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, so depend on that, you from
a receiver set, it will check and make sure that, yeah, I had received all the packets,
you send me, this is how it works, transfer level level level level, oh wait, transfer
level or services, connection node enter service here, so it is always a connection
or the enter services, if you want to go, ok, so here, transfer layer service to add
two ways to communicate, either TCP or UDP, I hope you know, in previous section we
talk about this, so it's either a TCP or other CUDP, TCP is more connection oriented
and it will give a security of that data will reach two destination, while in connection
less, it is not that connection less, as I said, it is not that make sure, make sure that
data will reach other destination, however the speed of a connection layer service, which
is a UDP is more, but in TCP, which is connection oriented is less, so everything is their
own advantage and disadvantage, depending on your services, depending on your requirement
you have to go with that, what's called a hold of a sign, due to its critical role in
end-to-end communication reliability, ok, so we communicate as a UDP or other TCP, so
basically we are connecting with a transport here, ok, now you can use less, if my system
is connected to anything, any device, it's through as TCP or UDP, ok, so now you know
that TCP or UDP is in a transport layer, so that's why it's called hurt of for the same
model, unbelievable, huh, so now you had to understand that by its quote and just remember
what it do, what is functionality, because a lot of interface asks you about transport
layer, because it's important, let's move there, not only here, so you are a network guy,
you have to understand it for a layer, network layer has two primary functions breaking
segments into network packets and reassembling them and re-rocketing packets by discovering
the optimal path across a physical network, we to use network address operators to
route packet to the destination, now you know, that what it's role and what it do, this
layer handle data transmission between host location and the development of it also manage
package routing, how it will do, sorry packet routing, how it will do, by the use of IP
and by the use of shortest path, there will be a algorithm of discusural rhythm, I think,
which will decide the shortest path in the network, okay, now it will choose the routing
of shortest path, and most of us know path of orbit routes, the sender is our both, receiver
IPDS are placed in the header, so if when you network layer is the one that transport,
the fragment from transport layer to below, it will add the source IPDS destination IPDS
and then the end tell that from this route you have to go, okay, so these are the information
it is given there, now in data link layer, it received the data and this calls for a step
you see and confirm any connection between two physical character nodes on network, it
will break packet into frames, now it will break the packets into frames and send them
from source to destination, it may, it's meant function is stored error free data transfer
but even the nodes, what a physical layer, when a packet arrives the data link layer ensure
it transmission to the correct host using its MAC address, yeah, the DLL data link layer
consists of two sub layers, logical link layer, MDXs, control, now MAC, it is the one that
is always a parameter test, of any system, however you can change it, you have to do a lot
of unethical things, which will not affect the system, but it will break the MAC address
for system and make your system very until as well, so logical link control identify network
protocol perform errors checking and synchronize frames, remember what it will do, MAC address
use MAC address to connect to device and defines permission for data transmission reception,
device framing, organize raw pit stream into frames by touching special bit pattern to
peg any and the making being meaningful to the receiver, you know receiver will have a lot
of information as the data pass from top layer to bottom, a packet have a lot of information
from IP address to MAC address to frame number from how it should be organized, everything
ok, so in the next video, in the next course, we will be a deep network course, if you
saw your love to me, I will make in which I will tell you which frame which byte contain
which data and which address, so in a very little manner, no data link data for data
link layer functions, physical addressing is there error control is there access control
is a flow control is a we know flow control, we know error control, what is X or global
multiple device, say a single channel, ok, the MAC sub layer minus channel access preventing
collision in certain phases, this is critical serial metal media network like ethernet,
this is how it works, physical address is also known as MAC address, no last one is physical
layer, the first layer of course, I model handle the physical electrical specter from
communication into the transmission, deception overload database 0 and 1, remember the
first video of course, machine communicate either in a 0 or other no file, in a binary
way, so here we back to a binary format over a transmitted search as a copper wire, fiber
optics over a channel, so this is the form the foundation of one we should either go
to the web, so either the wired network, rather wireless network, one from one device show
another device, it will go, so it will, so our data in a bits, now it will convert into
electronic, ok, in a electronic frames, you know electronic that it will pass through
as a current, as a electricity, it will pass through a wire or wireless medium, right,
we have two magnetic waves, so it will pass from that channel going from my system to
access point to access switch to distance switch to courses to firewall now goes out
to my company, to my corporate office, now hey it is going to be Google DNS, ok, so this
is how it works, service that physical layer provide maintaining the rate of data flow,
synchronization bits, very important, controlling bit rate processing physical signal
and direct, taking data transfer, deciding network topology, forwarding a record a lot
of things that you will do, so what will be the advantage, so this is only layer in which
I add advantage and disadvantage, because many interview want you to know basic, this course
is for a corporate employees as well as the one that who is preparing for the job, so
I add the important thing as well, because as a fresher, I know you don't know much
on network, but I want you to know basic, so I will always ask you, tell me the advantage
of physical layer, disadvantage of physical layer, either either either tell me the what
is physical layer, ok, so advantages, standard digestion, ensure interpret between different
devices and manufacturing, foundation provided essential hardware and connected data, all
higher network layer really upon the function, versus relative work across various media
type include copper wire fiber optics wireless radio waves, high speed motor physical media
or support very high speed long-distance data transmission, bit synchronization, manage
the timing, data it, ensure accurate data transfer between secondary server, disadvantage,
no error correction, it does not detect the effects added in data transfer, it simply
transmit robots, so simply robots 01, physical one would be suspectable to damage from
an on-factor, physical tempering or competitive way, it can be a wire cut, it can be
any device issue, it can be anything, single degradation prone to issue like noise interface
I have to listen, yeah if you have access point and there is a laptop and there is a wall
between that or there is a thick glass, the gate between them or wall between them, then
it will affect, signal degradation, degradation is there, no data intelligence, yes
from it differently, because it will transfer, there it will not check, there is no intelligence
there, circuit test is always there, no, we talk about data link theory basically, get
into more of that, data link layer always a packet at this layer referred as a frame,
double, we did a make up in our transport layer, we make a, no, not in the transport layer,
there is a referred as a frame, device like switches and bracelet operated at a data link,
it is always always occurs, it is 3, write it down, which network device work on data
link layer, which network device work on network layer, so this is always stuck, switch
and braces operated at a data link layer, functionality is primarily handled by NIC, network
interface card, we talked about in previous video and host machine device drivers, okay,
physical data sensor, okay this is all about the road transmission and the physical connection
or wireless cable connection, it is bit synchronisation, bit rate control is the important
factor here, now key physical effect devices, hubby, peter, modem, network cables are used
in this layer, okay this layer, home of the data in network layer are known as a low, low
lower layer or hardware layer, as we talked in the graph, physical deploys is a space
for network arrangement, yes bus, star, mass topologies, transmission modes, defenseless
data type, either a simple or higher data place, we talked about this as well, no advantage
of OSI model, everything is in a very layered and format wired way, stick it, layered approach,
the wired network connection to seven days in layer, simplifying, and extending a triple
sort of complex system, each layer has specified and fixed functionalities, standardisation,
promote, standardised network communication as each layer adheres to different protocols
firsting, interpretally between different vendor products, easy diagnose, we know that what
which layer perform, which functionalities, so we can easily diagnose according to it, first
in network problem, diagnose problem, engineer to assert, issue, respect, load, instrument,
turbo-soding, operating and reducing time, improves capability, allow for independent
updates and improvement within each layer without affecting other supporting technology
advancement and features, it's capabilities at best thing in this model, no, TCP, IP model,
the back well of the internet, OSI is a vertical framework, so it is just to understand
how, packet, how frames, how everything is working in a network, but the practical protocol
suite that is actually is used for a communication, in a global network is TCP/IP model,
no, as you can see there is a TCP/OS/IP, what is a TCP and what is IP, TCP's Stanford
Transmissive Control Protocol, instead accurate and reliable delivery of data, it manage connection
statement, data segmentation, flow control and error checking, what it do, connection
stress placement, data segmentation, flow control and error checking, parenting data
arrive completely and in order, what is IP, internal protocol, handle the logical addressing
and routing of a data, packet across network, it is responsible for finding the correct
destination address, every system have a internet, internet, have a in a locally written
network, in your corporate, have IP address, so everyone have different IP address, so
it will decide that where it is and how I have present routing, path, I have to choose,
together TCP and I perform the TCP/IP protocol suite enable end-to-end connectivity and data
transfer across diverse network, so TCP for connection and data transfers through IP.
Now, in TCP, UDP, user data protocol, offers a connectionless faster data for data transmission
where it will be scheduled, how TCP is inherited, clicker and IP does for its IP transmission
of operation, for its operation, so this is how a TCP/IP model works, there is a network
of access layer, internet layer, transfer layer and application layer.
Layer of TCP, network access layer, combine the OSI, physical and data layer, so
we combine the bottom two of OSM model and make a network access layer, handle physical
infrastructure and technical aspect like converting digital data into transmit all signals.
Then, there is an internet layer and logos to the OSI network layer, manage logical addressing,
IP does the routing and ensuring data reaches each transmission across the internet, transfer
layer, hardware size and hardware size IP model, gets one into the OSI transfer layer
for a reliable data transfer segmentation assembly and error fake communication between
application.
Yes, it is application layer at the top most of the same layer.
In comparison though, we say session, presentation application layer, three things, okay.
Entire directly with the end user application enabling service like web browsing, we will
see a diagram as well, let's move more into a network, share layer and entire layer.
So this layer sometimes refers to as a detected layer in the TCP/IP context, manage the physical
spectrum for the converter communication over the internet, the physical ethernet cable
survival network, network interface current and device devices, device drivers, this is possible
for technical conversation conversion of a digital data into transfer symbols, we have
you have digital data and you have to transfer to a transmitter signals, so you can send
it through a wire or wireless media, making the network possible.
Just see how network is so unbelievable things that you can't imagine these things happening
like this, okay.
So let us in your 90s, you are sitting and someone telling you this thing, this is how
a data will transfer, this is how everything will work or flow in an air.
You can say that, how is it possible if I can't see the data, how it will transform your
system to another system, it's kind of impossible, you will think, definitely I will
do the same, but it's working, it's also known as the network layer, it's primarily
used to control the flow and routing of traffic, important mode in down control the flow
and routing of traffic, ensuring data is significantly and accurately across and interconnected
network.
It's also responsible for assembling fragment data packets at the decision, where hydrophic
might certainly increase transmission time, this layer prioritize accuracy minimizing the
user's data correction, it defines the protocol for logical data transmission over the
entire network.
Now, what is the key protocol of internet here?
We have internet protocol, IP, I say MP, internet protocol message protocol, and AFP,
address visitors from protocol.
So these are the key protocols of the internet layer, IP.
The fundamental protocol for delivering the packet for source to destination was its
inspect IP addresses in packet head to head by the current path, IP has to primary
was an IPv4 IPv6, we will talk about this in a leaderboard is IPv4 is a most well used
right now, but it's a limited, so we are not in a future we develop new with IPv6 in
every device, but right now we have IPv4 in my system, in my computer, at the same time
I can see IPv6 in my mobile as well, but how would we in operate, we right now working
in an IPv4 always, it isn't a, it is the imitation of IPv4 offering of the state expanded
the space to accommodate the cooling number of internet connected device, did not control
message protocol, encapsulate with data, IP data, ground, I simply is a vital network
technology to get power host with information about network problems such as industrial
destination of packet timeout tools like ping and test out how they will be on the
simple, yes, I simply so I don't know you do it or not, when you do a ping to go in, he
don't data data, or four, two, two, two, two, so there is a four dot two, two, two,
three part away, so it will use SMP protocol, now area, area, P video, critical function
is a map and a appeal address logical address to physical address.
Okay, so do you have a, you get a IP address when you connect to a network and there is
a MAC address in your system, so it will the one that will map both to each other on
a local network, someone a attainable IP packet to a hilly to order to address so it
have a repeatable, yeah, so you have a repeatable, now on the
basis of that it will decide that, okay, so this system is present here and I have to
send it to him, so this is how routing is going, this is how packet is moved to your
system, not instead of going to your friend's system, so this is how work, this enable IP
packet to correlate to the target device, and I see, if we end up with a cloud not able
a repeat type in good, proxy, rp, and radius rp, so this is a in a transport rate, as
a, there's a TCP and UDP, I meet a just a little bit more in a detail, you can pause
a video, you have to read once like, you have a major 4 to 5 difference that you have
to remember, that's it, and why it is used and where in which application which is used,
that's just, I'm going to move it, here it is, application there of TCP model having
application presented in a social layer of the same model, transport rate or heard is always
heard, other in both layer, and in network layer is converted into an internet layer, network
in a social sphere is consists of data layer physically, let's move ahead, so yeah, the
understand KCP, the internet foundation, here, the transmission control protocol, what
right people to call, internet protocol, model is the fundamental support for the communication
protocol used for the internet, similar component, where it ticket, how data is formed,
at this transmitter, router ratio, the model insert, reliability, and to it communication
by wagging it on return to management packet, transmitting them across the network and
assembly, there's data station, this is the whole definition that you have to tell, whenever
they ask, tell me the TCP IP model, or define what is TCP IP model, this is a proper
definition, that's why I, in this course you have seen that sometime, I repeat many things,
because I want you to remember that this is how I have to tell, if you're going to define
TCP IP model in this definition, amazing, amazing, as an interview, as let us, I went over
the anima, I'm someone giving me this, as an answer, I'm going to select him per 100%.
Let's move ahead, a quick comparison between those, TCP, transmission control protocol,
remember the full form, OSA, open system, interconnection, layer consolidation, combine
session layer parallelization within the application layer, maintain separation, representation,
follow our connection list, horizontal approach in a design, follow our vertical, hierarchical
approach, packet delivery center does not enable the guarantee packet delivery of the transformer,
it translates as a shock for a shock packet delivery, protocol, flexibility, protocol are
entirely integrated and not easily replaceable, protocol are well defined and can be more easily
shocked as a technology works, connection interfaces only provide connection less services
to it, transport it, provide both connection layer, as connect your data, success within
a dog layer, so you have to understand the difference between the TCP model, which is
a product for network present and that's it for now, thank you very much, whatever you
have go through this course, whatever you go through, this actually video, video is completed,
write it down, write it down, whatever you have in your mind, it may be around, it may be
direct, you have to decide it later, but for now make a TCP IP, TCP architecture, make
a OSA architecture, tell by own what is which layer, which layer perform, but how a data
is communicating, how your system is communicating, visualise everything, okay, visualise
everything.
Thank you very much, we will meet in our next video, bye bye.